<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>elijahcaine.me - creative-writing</title><link href="elijahcaine.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="elijahcaine.me/feeds/creative-writing.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>elijahcaine.me/</id><updated>2016-09-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Lady Wangle</title><link href="elijahcaine.me/lady-wangle" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-09-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Elijah Voigt</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-09-14:elijahcaine.me/lady-wangle</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;A baroness looks at the Mona Lisa and sees her newborn baby in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="prompt"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prompt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A baroness looks at the Mona Lisa and sees her newborn baby in the
background. - &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/MagicRealismBot/status/768207599468634113"&gt;MagicRealismBot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lady Wangle (of the prestigious Canadian Royalty) flew to the Louvre for her
27th birthday.  In past visits she had always marveled at the beautiful marble
statutes, historic illustrations, and the grandiose building itself.  She
always loved the glass pyramid, even if she didn't really see how it fit with
the rest of the architecture.  The Louvre was a special place in her heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She wanted to bring her newborn daughter &lt;em&gt;Anna&lt;/em&gt; with but her husband &lt;em&gt;Harold&lt;/em&gt;
was concerned about the baby flying only two months after being born.  L.W.
offered to cancel the trip but he insisted that she go saying &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Sweetie,
you've been taking care of this baby for nine months.  You can take a week
off.  You deserve it.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;  L.W. wasn't one to fight over things like this so she
packed for a three-day trip and went off to Paris.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an early riser, or perhaps just a jet-lagged riser -- she always wanted to
be an early riser but it wasn't in her genes.  Regardless, she was up early.
She didn't like the dark of mid January mornings, but that animosity was more
or less evened out by her love of being alone in the quiet frigid winter air.
She saw that the museum wouldn't open for another two hours and so she
adventured toward the big Ferris Wheel East of the museum.  She ultimately
intended to walk by the riverfront but settled for seeing some sights first.
She hadn't been to Paris in many years and was curious to see how it had
changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To her disappointment nothing had really changed in Paris.  She supposed that
was part of the charm; it was tastefully timeless.  One could come back year
after year and get the same Paris they'd gotten before.  Friends could visit
separately and talk about some hole-in-the-wall cafe they'd found independent
of one-another.  Any city built on a certain level of tourism &lt;strong&gt;had&lt;/strong&gt; to keep
the high-lights stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The museum opened and a small line had started to form.  She got in line and
held idle chit-chat with a couple from Dallas, Texas.  Their names were
Jeffery and Matilda Almond. They were eager to share that this was their way
of celebrating their 30th Anniversary with &lt;em&gt;'the honeymoon they never had'&lt;/em&gt;.
L.W. asked who was partial to seeing the Louvre to which Jeff proudly
exclaimed &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;It was all Matilda.  She got a degree in ART ya' know -- she's
real smart.  Most of this stuff goes way over my head but she's there to
explain it to me.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;  Matilda blushed, she was the quiet one and Jeff was the
loud one of the pair, but she could tell they got along anyway.  L.W. smiled
at this and with that the conversation awkwardly petered out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;L.W. always made a bee-line for the Mona Lisa when she went to the Louvre.
She made the mistake of meandering there on one of her trips but by the time
she got to it it was too crowded (&lt;em&gt;only two hours after opening!&lt;/em&gt;) to see it.
She raced all of the Asian tourist families with their massive &lt;em&gt;Canon DSLR&lt;/em&gt;
cameras and was one of the first pairs of eyes to see it that day.  She took
it all in, noting yet again how much smaller it looks in real-life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wave after wave she took the piece in.  She knew there were better paintings
in the Louvre but something resonated with her about the &lt;em&gt;Mona Lisa&lt;/em&gt;.
Something was special, some connection... was that... was that Anna in the
background?  L.W.  peered at the piece and realized that an exact replication
of her daughter --&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm sorry reader.  I can't do it.  I built this up too much and now... now the
... I'm not even sure what to call it. The punchline? It doesn't make any
sense.  I know the point of the MagicRealismBot stories isn't to make
something that &lt;em&gt;makes sense&lt;/em&gt; in a logical sense, but like... it should at
least be &lt;em&gt;consistent&lt;/em&gt; and actions should be justified.  I'm not trying to
write an &lt;strong&gt;'and then'&lt;/strong&gt; story I'm trying to write a &lt;strong&gt;'therefore, and so'&lt;/strong&gt;
story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I apologize.  This was just a bad story to begin with.  I avoided the prompt
for the majority of it anyway.  I even ignored that I had started this for
almost three weeks, hoping I'd come back and the story would magically &lt;em&gt;become
better&lt;/em&gt;.  I know that's not &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; a bad thing, but in this case it
wasn't a good sign -- delaying the inevitable usually means one is dread it.
That is kind of a necessity with these, take what you like from a prompt and
push the rest to the side, barely quantifying the thing as 'written from the
prompt'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I'm rambling now.  Thank you for reading, it means a lot.  I'll try to
do something more -- I don't know --  &lt;strong&gt;more better&lt;/strong&gt; in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="creative-writing"></category><category term="Creative Writing"></category><category term="MagicRealismBot"></category></entry><entry><title>Paperweight on my shoulders</title><link href="elijahcaine.me/paperweight-on-my-shoulders" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-30T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-08-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Elijah Voigt</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-08-30:elijahcaine.me/paperweight-on-my-shoulders</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;A paperweight whispers to a mathematician: &amp;quot;I feel so depressed.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="prompt"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prompt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A paperweight whispers to a mathematician: &amp;quot;I feel so depressed.&amp;quot; -
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/MagicRealismBot/status/770382059319595008"&gt;MagicRealismBot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fredrick Gustav was working well into the night as he was known to do in the
weeks preceding a publication of his work.  When he worked deep into the night
he took a drug called Caffeine in various forms from liquid to pill form to
stay awake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the long nights he was also known to converse with furniture and inanimate
objects around the room which were up for a quick chat as he needed to rest.
If his 'people skills' were more astute (and there were people around to see
him) Fredrick might be embarrassed by his own behavior but the pros really did
outweigh the cons this late at night.  His bookshelf had many interesting
things to say but could sometimes overwhelm him.  His chair was also good to
talk with, but didn't get out much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tonight Fredrick's paperweight decided to speak up.  It was a small manatee
Beanie Baby and it started the conversation similar to how his bottom drawer
tended to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I feel so depressed.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fredrick was shocked by the plush manatee.  It had never spoken up before and
quite frankly he wasn't sure it was able to until just now.  After the shock
subsided he responded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Well you're a new voice.  What might your name be there beanie baby manatee?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BBM sighed and reflected on the question but was unable to answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Do you have a name?  You've been around this office for almost a year now, it
seems about time I learned what to call you.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BBM responded positively to this idea and so Fredrick began the search for a
name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Well, it seems like &lt;em&gt;Snooty&lt;/em&gt; is a pretty famous manatee in Florida.  Mind if
I call you that?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BBM responded shyly &amp;quot;Yeah... that sounds okay...&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fredrick, not picking up on the hesitation in BBM's voice, carried on proud of
his naming abilities and ready for the rest of the night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Wonderful.  So my next question is 'Why do you feel depressed Snooty?'&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snooty, who had not yet fully accepted the name, felt it was obvious why.  She
had been stuck in this office for over a year and why?  She was bought by a
mother and daughter and had &lt;em&gt;hoped&lt;/em&gt; that she would be adopted by them, but of
course she ended up being taken in by an old fart like Fredrick.  She couldn't
tell him that but it was how she felt.  Somehow she wanted to get out of here
and into the &lt;em&gt;real world&lt;/em&gt;.  She wanted to go to the park with a kid who named
her something infinitely more creative than 'Snooty'.  She wanted to go on
adventures and see wonders of the world outside people called &lt;em&gt;Cincinnati&lt;/em&gt;.
Despite her fear of his reaction she quickly mustered up the gumption to tell
Fredrick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I'm depressed because... because I'm stuck in this office when I could be on
adventures with a kid.  Adventures like... like I'm supposed to be on.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fredrick reflected on this for a while.  Glancing between her and the seventh
draft of his publication. He finally spoke up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I understand.  If I were you I'd want to get out of this office too.  Maybe
my daughter can find a good home for you, she works with children.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snooty was very excited at this prospect and if she could physically smile she
would have just then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few hours later Fredrick called it a night, packed up his things, and went
home with Snooty in his briefcase.  He arrive home at almost 2:47am and left
Snooty in the keys bowl.  He felt sad sometimes, coming home late to an empty
house.  Even his paper weight didn't like him, how could expect his wife and
children to do the same.  But he got up the next morning and did it all again.
At least he'd have his office to keep him company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="creative-writing"></category><category term="Creative Writing"></category><category term="MagicRealismBot"></category></entry><entry><title>The MoonStone discovery</title><link href="elijahcaine.me/the-moonstone-discovery" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-08-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Elijah Voigt</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-08-19:elijahcaine.me/the-moonstone-discovery</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;By looking at a fireplace, a medieval sorcerer can turn stone into moonstones.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="prompt"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prompt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
By looking at a fireplace, a medieval sorcerer can turn stone into
moonstones.  &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/MagicRealismBot/status/766606956295356420"&gt;MagicRealismBot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ellyn scrambled to take notes as fast as she could.  She had finally found a
way to produce &lt;strong&gt;MoonStone&lt;/strong&gt; and it would change &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;!  With
&lt;strong&gt;MoonStone&lt;/strong&gt; one could turn sand into gold, the living into the dead, and
countless other &lt;em&gt;theoretical&lt;/em&gt; properties she had read of.  Now that she was
able to produce that which had alluded sorcerers since the dawn of knowledge
the sky was the limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She took her quill and parchment and wrote furiously.  She described in great
detail the position of the Sun in the Sky, the time of year, where she stood in
the room and where the room stood on Earth.  She knew every detail wouldn't be
important but every detail &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be so they all must be recorded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standing my robes, staring intently at 12 BoilingRocks in the fireplace,
facing head-first at the display.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sun stands high in a Summer's fore-noon, just glancing through the
window unto the fireplace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After the duration of approximately three Hail Mary's the stones turned
white and fragile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rocks no-doubt turned into &lt;strong&gt;MoonStones&lt;/strong&gt; as was theorized.  Their
shape and texture proves it so.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The MoonStones glow faint white, matte and with hints of spiritual
aura.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;MoonStones&lt;/strong&gt; weigh substantially less than the BoilingRocks did,
perhaps losing mass in the process of transformation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As she finished writing her findings she grabbed her wax and seal and marked
it to be delivered to her mentor Rowan.  He had spent the better part of his
long life (&lt;em&gt;76 years young!&lt;/em&gt;) attempting to find the secret to producing
&lt;strong&gt;MoonStone&lt;/strong&gt; from earthly materials but had come up empty-handed.  Ellyn felt
proud of her findings and was glad to be able to share it with Rowan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moments later Ellyn sent off her findings with a sample of the &lt;strong&gt;MoonStone&lt;/strong&gt;
via the local carrier.  She told him to &lt;em&gt;take it with haste to Rowan&lt;/em&gt; and gave
the carrier an extra copper piece in hopes that he would.  The carrier ran off
down the road, the journey was almost a quarter day's travel so Ellyn returned
to her study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As she sat in wait studying the &lt;strong&gt;MoonStones&lt;/strong&gt;, she grew weary of her
findings.  Just a moment ago she was so sure of her discovery, but now that
she had sent off the finding she became... hesitant.  Was this &lt;strong&gt;MoonStone&lt;/strong&gt;
or perhaps the similar &lt;em&gt;SilverStone&lt;/em&gt;.  &lt;strong&gt;MoonStone&lt;/strong&gt; was only theoretical,
studied in the mind and never before in the hand; it had never been proven to
exist so what made her so sure that &lt;em&gt;this rock&lt;/em&gt; was what they had been
searching for.  She was, after all, just an apprentice sorcerer; what did she
know?  If Rowan determined her findings untrue what would stop him from
revoking his mentor ship?  Her years of study would be for naut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ellyn had always been prone to worry. She took a deep breath and with nothing
else to do, she sat in wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="creative-writing"></category><category term="Creative Writing"></category><category term="MagicRealismBot"></category></entry><entry><title>Debra the ghoul</title><link href="elijahcaine.me/debra-the-ghoul" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-07-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Elijah Voigt</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-07-02:elijahcaine.me/debra-the-ghoul</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;A ghoul and an archbishop are fighting over custody of their children.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="prompt"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prompt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A ghoul and an archbishop are fighting over custody of their children.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/MagicRealismBot/status/749301833881915392"&gt;MagicRealismBot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like every Friday night, Debra picked up her two daughters from her
ex-wife's house in Evanston and drove them downtown for the weekend.  As she
drove away in her red 2008 Corolla with them she got a text message from her
ex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From: Gwendolyn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Debra,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please bring Lilyan and Odell back by 9pm on Sunday.  They have school
Monday morning.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debra became immediately filled with rage.  &lt;em&gt;'Of course they both have school
Monday morning!  I'm not stupid!  I've been doing this for four and a half
years goddammit.  How stupid does she think I am?  Christ she can be such a
--'&lt;/em&gt; and before she went down that rabbit hole she remembered what her
therapist said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Just breath.  Everything is going to be okay.  This is just temporary.  Her
bitchy behavior only affects you if you let it.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debra drove a few more miles, her daughters in the back staying cautiously
silent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually Lilyan spoke up. &amp;quot;Debora, why does mommy so mean to you?&amp;quot;
deliberately calling Debra (or &lt;strong&gt;Debora&lt;/strong&gt; in Lilyan's case) by her name and
Gwen by &lt;em&gt;'mommy'&lt;/em&gt;.  This used to bug Debra but she eventually became apathetic
toward the situation.  Gwendolyn had brainwashed the kids; she was honestly
just glad she was able to fight and keep her daughters on the weekends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Why &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; mommy so mean to me. And sweety, I'm a ghoul and that means that
&lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; people don't really like me.&amp;quot; Debra said matter-of-factly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Like racism?&amp;quot; Lilyan asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Exactly like racism Lily.  And your mother is a Christian official called an
'Archbishop'.  For some reason, probably some squabble hundreds of years ago
[or maybe they've just always been biggots] none of your mother's bosses liked
that she was in a relationship me so she had to give it up.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a momentary pause as the girls thought this over.  Lilyan was six
and Odell was eight, neither of which were really prepared to fully process
what she was saying, but she wanted them to feel respected and independent so
she participated in their questions.  They were both technically Gwendolyn's
daughters with a donor, Debra would have had child if she was able to but
ghouls had a notorously difficult time doing anything related to &lt;em&gt;living&lt;/em&gt;,
creating life included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;But why does she not like you?&amp;quot; Lilyan finally asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debra sighed.  &amp;quot;Well, I think she doesn't like me because she wishes we could
still be together.  We had a very romantic fling in the beginning and we
really thought we could stay together but... well it wasn't meant to last.
She just thinks that this is the best way to deal with the situation.  Some
people would rather feel angry than sad.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lilyan quickly followed up with the obvious &amp;quot;Do you feel sad Debora?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debra thought for a moment. Lilyan asked again &amp;quot;Do you feel sad Debora?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sometimes sweetie.  Sometimes I feel very sad and it makes it very hard to do
things like go to work and eat food.  Most of the time that happens I remind
myself how lucky I am to have you two to look forward to.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lilyan didn't know what else to ask and so the three sat in silence as they
drove down Lake-Shore Drive.  The lamp posts cast yellow-tinged shadows on
their faces as they each looked out the windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Odell finally spoke up, &amp;quot;What are we going to do this weekend?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Good question.  What do you guys want to do?  I was thinking we could go
mini-golfing once you get your homework done.  How does that sound?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They both groaned. Debra smiled &amp;quot;Well I guess it's settled. Mini putt-putt
tomorrow afternoon.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="creative-writing"></category><category term="Creative Writing"></category><category term="MagicRealismBot"></category></entry><entry><title>Emperor Stan of Stantinople</title><link href="elijahcaine.me/emperor-stan-of-stantinople" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Elijah Voigt</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-07-01:elijahcaine.me/emperor-stan-of-stantinople</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;An emperor owns a steam-powered device which allows him to destroy the past.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="prompt"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prompt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
An emperor owns a steam-powered device which allows him to destroy the
past.  &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/MagicRealismBot/status/749120629308203009"&gt;MagicRealismBot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emperor Stan of Stantinople, the most prosperous 1500 square feet in all of
&lt;strong&gt;Oak Burch Sunrise Shire&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Suburban [Gated] Community&lt;/em&gt;, ruled with an &lt;em&gt;iron
fist&lt;/em&gt; and an endless stream of &lt;em&gt;Puns&lt;/em&gt;.  His wife and three daughters obeyed
his every whim, when it fit their schedules... and if they were in a good
mood... and they wanted to.  Stan was content with his life as an emperor and
ruler of his domain, no matter how far and wide that domain spanned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One Tuesday afternoon, as he stood at the edge of the sidewalk squinting
toward his back yard and telling himself that &lt;em&gt;'Stantinople stretches as far
as the eye can see'&lt;/em&gt;, his mind drifted to the life he could have had.  He
thought about all of the mistakes he had made like when he tried stand-up and
totally bombed, when he got into massive debt from college and dropped out,
and when he bought a house in the suburbs -- the mistakes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seemingly out of nowhere he was tapped on the nose by a delivery woman.  She
told him to sign her PDA and before he could process what was happening she
dropped a thick wooden, about the size of a bedside table, at his doorstep.
He turned around and the woman sped away in an un-marked FedEx van; it didn't
say FedEx, because it was unmarked, but the color and shape was right so Stan
figured it probably was FedEx.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He lugged the box into the house and down to the finished basement he (and a
poster in the stairwell leading down to the basement) called the
&lt;strong&gt;'Stantinople Man Cave'&lt;/strong&gt;, despite it not having many &lt;em&gt;Man Cave&lt;/em&gt; amenities
nor being an actual cave for which one might find men.  The entirety of the
basement consisted of three dark brown leather couches lined up in an 'L'
formation in the corner and a small, almost child-sized foosball table on the
opposite end of the room.  He didn't even invest in a wide-screen TV and a few
Lay-Z boy chairs with built-in mini-fridges!  Stan really had no concept of
what a &lt;em&gt;Man Cave&lt;/em&gt; ought to have but nobody really called him on it since he
was obviously trying his sad 43 year-old best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He fumbled the box with a &lt;em&gt;WHOOMP&lt;/em&gt; onto the carpet and painlessly opened it
with its &lt;em&gt;No Hassle™ packaging&lt;/em&gt;, an innovation he did not realized had made
its way to wooden packaging.  Removing the item Stan thought this new device
was a sewing machine and he got excited, but upon closer inspection he
realised it was not a sewing machine.  The device was a rectangular cube with
rounded edges and was hollow in the middle except for what looked like some
pistons; the device was matt black and had four rubber feet on the bottom and
was branded &lt;em&gt;'Past Scrubber'&lt;/em&gt;.  He lifted the device out of the box and
flipped 'on' the devices only switch; it began to &lt;em&gt;whurrrrrr&lt;/em&gt; like a small
engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stan rummaged through the box and found a piece of paper which read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
May this device only be used by the mightiest and wisest emperors.  With
its mechanical power it may erase both mistakes and triumphs of the past.
It does not discriminate, this is the job of its master.  You are its
master.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sweet! This thing looks cool.&amp;quot; Stan said oblivious to the ominous tone of
this note. &amp;quot;Let's see... it can change the past.  I wonder what I should
change...&amp;quot; he said foolishly not taking this very serious device seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Well first I'd wish I'd never moved out to the suburbs.  That was a huge
mistake.&amp;quot; The machine's &lt;em&gt;whurrr&lt;/em&gt;'ing intensified and an instant later he found
himself living in a nice apartment near down-town.  Since time had been
altered, and in this universe you don't remember old timeliness if you change
the past (deal with it), Stan had no idea that anything had changed and had
yet to make his first decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Well first I'd wish I never went to college, that was a huge waste of time
just to drop out.&amp;quot; and again (for you, not for him) the machine &lt;em&gt;whurrr&lt;/em&gt;'d
louder and an instant later Stan found himself in a much shittier apartment,
further from downtown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Well first I'd wish I went to college, I really could have done something
with my life.&amp;quot; and the machine didn't respond because, despite it's visual
similarities to a sewing machine, the device only knew how to destroy time and
not how to create it.  He would have known this if he read the freaking manual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stan quickly grew bored with the device after naming off a few things he
&lt;em&gt;wished&lt;/em&gt; he had done and it just &lt;em&gt;whurr&lt;/em&gt;'ing on.  He switched the machine
&lt;em&gt;off&lt;/em&gt; and put it in the corner and muttered to himself &amp;quot;Maybe I can get
something for it on ebay.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a furious bidding war between two hobbyist mechanics Stan got $153 for
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Not bad.&amp;quot; He said when the bidding ended. &amp;quot;Not bad indeed.&amp;quot; and smiled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="creative-writing"></category><category term="Creative Writing"></category><category term="MagicRealismBot"></category></entry><entry><title>Character Study: The 'try new things' couple</title><link href="elijahcaine.me/the-try-new-things-couple" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-06-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2016-06-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Elijah Voigt</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-06-17:elijahcaine.me/the-try-new-things-couple</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Gwendolyn and Stefan love to try new things...&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Gwendolyn and Stefan love to try new things.  Not like... &lt;em&gt;sex things&lt;/em&gt;, but
like &lt;em&gt;lifestyle things&lt;/em&gt;.  Take, for example, Gwendolyn decided last week that
she would love to see what life was like if she and Stefan only shared &lt;strong&gt;one&lt;/strong&gt;
bowl, plate, cup, fork, knife, spoon, and pan for a month. She didn't really
have a good reason for &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; at the time, it's not like she read it in a
magazine or anything, but they're young and into wacky stuff like that.  Stefan
always participates in these and likes talking about their &lt;em&gt;adventures&lt;/em&gt; as
they're happening, but never proposes ideas of his own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gwendolyn requires that people use the full &lt;em&gt;Gwendolyn&lt;/em&gt; and not &lt;em&gt;Gwen&lt;/em&gt; and has
been known to &lt;strong&gt;halt&lt;/strong&gt; conversations if people don't. She feels was confident
that she loves Stefan three times more than he loves her.  She wasn't sure why
she felt that way, or where three times came from, but it had always been her
hunch.  Since she's never been able to confirm or deny it, she has kept on
believing it; this puts her in an artificially smug mood whenever she
sacrifices something for Stefan, like the 5% markup on the organic foods
because he prefers them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stefan previously refereed to her as &lt;em&gt;Gwen&lt;/em&gt; internally but forced himself to
adapt after a few preventable meltdowns.  He hasn't ever really considered how
much he loves Gwendolyn, but he regularly thinks about the house they'll buy
together in a few years.  There isn't actually a specific house they're
thinking about, but he still enjoys the fantasy; some women dream of their
wedding day and Stefan dreams of his move-in day.  Year after year they've
stayed in the same mid-town loft and will never did move into that house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They both definitely &lt;strong&gt;love&lt;/strong&gt; each other to the extent that any
twenty-somethings can love one another while still collectively managing to
avoid the question of marriage.  They will eventually break-up, not because of
any one event or central cause, but because people grow up and grow apart.
It's never anybody's fault, it's just how the wind blows.  Some people's
connections are able to persevere that inevitable break, but this connection
will not.  Gwendolyn knows this and in the back of her head is already thinking
about why a breakup would be best for them.  Stefan has thought about it once
or twice but doesn't really want things to change.  He likes spending his life
with Gwendolyn and feels like they do share a really close bond, even if that
bond is largely based on things like sharing one bowl, plate, cup, fork, knife,
spoon, and pan for a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, the &lt;em&gt;sharing-one-of-everything&lt;/em&gt; thing is working out pretty well.
Gwendolyn hasn't gotten any of their friends to try it but she really feels
like she's looking at food and meals in a whole new light.  Stefan thinks it's
a neat idea, but is looking forward to the end of this month.  He would
never tell her that though.  He loves her too much.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="creative-writing"></category><category term="Creative Writing"></category><category term="Character Study"></category></entry></feed>