<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>elijahcaine.me - housing</title><link href="elijahcaine.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="elijahcaine.me/feeds/housing.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>elijahcaine.me/</id><updated>2022-01-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Buying a House Part 3: Renovation Station!</title><link href="elijahcaine.me/buying-a-house-03-renovation-station" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-04T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2022-01-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Elijah Voigt</name></author><id>tag:None,2022-01-04:elijahcaine.me/buying-a-house-03-renovation-station</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Basically just bragging about the stuff I've done to my house so far.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is part 3 of a 4 part series on buying a home&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;em&gt;Check out part 1 for to start from the beginning&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations!
You slogged through finding, trying to buy, and then successfully buying a house.
Give yourself a pat on the back because that is an impressive feat you've accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is more of a personal post than the others covering the renovations we've made to our house in the first year.
I hope it helps illustrate some of the pros (and cons) of being able to do whatever the heck you want when you own the place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="let-s-fuck-up-this-yard"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Let's fuck up this yard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best part of our house has been the back yard.
I'm writing this post from my standing desk on my back patio, our doggo loves playing fetch in the yard, and we even started a garden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="patiooooo"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Patiooooo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first project was to build a stone patio.
Not some half-assed &amp;quot;throw some rocks on the ground and call it good&amp;quot; thing, but some real HGTV quality shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucy of course did all of the research, planning, and purchasing of materials.
I moved a bunch of rocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we could build the patio we had to dig 7&amp;quot; of dirt out from the ground, which is non-trivial.
We invited some friends, bought Thai food, and got to work in late October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: 7&amp;quot; of dirt for a 10&amp;quot;x16&amp;quot; hole is a shit-ton of dirt.
We eventually had to rent one of those big metal waste disposal bins you usually see in front of houses or other construction sites.
Of course then we had to move the dirt a second time from piles in our yard to the bin, but then it was gone for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we dug out the dirt we were able to fill it back in with rocks (pebbles) then smaller rocks (sand) and finally pavers, which is what the industry calls short cube rocks -- not to be confused with bricks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hardest part was definitely making everything flat.
The pavers are big squares, which I though would be forgiving if the underlying sand and gravel wasn't flat, but wow I was wrong.
Eventually I found my groove and got very zen about making the sand flat.
We used used a 10' 2x4 and dragged it across our layer of sand in a variety of patterns until eventually it was &amp;quot;flat enough&amp;quot;.
In retrospect it was kinda fun.
Very calming once you submit to the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally we put the pavers down, filled the cracks with polymeric sand (which is just &amp;quot;concrete lite&amp;quot;), and sealed that bitch up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole project took a few weeks and cost about 1k for materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We almost gave up at the end when we realized making things flat was way harder than expected.
The quote to get the project finished, which was 90% done, was around 5k which gave us heart-burn so we stubbornly finished it ourselves.
So it turns out we saved ~5k by doing this project ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this I'm game to do any home project myself as long as it doesn't involve electricity and plumbing in the walls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="baby-you-re-a-fiiiireee-pit"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Baby you're a fiiiireee-pit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A comparatively small project was our fire pit.
This was just a fire ring with some bricks stacked on the outside.
Very safe, very simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly it was nice to get a quick win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="big-ass-raised-bed"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Big ass raised bed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also built a big ass raised bed.
It's 4'x12' and it gets a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of sun.
Also a quick win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything feels like a quick win after building that fucking patio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="new-hvac-who-this"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New HVAC, who this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December ancient gas furnace ran out of diesel, resulting in not having heat... funny how that works.
This is usually trivial to solve: you call a company and they fill your gas tank and charge you a few hundo.
With gas in the tank your heat comes back on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple people talked about how great the furnace we had was.
It was installed with the house, so it was at least 70 years old and it did work well.
The heat that came out of the vents was super hot, but it also ran on gasoline in a tank in our basement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm sure the carbon footprint of my home's gas heating is negligible when compared to the carbon footprint of every flight I take, but Lucy and I decided if we &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; get rid of it we &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;.
We did some research on alternatives and decided an electric Heat-Pump would be a good alternative.
It would provide us with heat &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; cooling, and wouldn't run on diesel; the only downside is it'd be expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few things:
1. A Heat-Pump is a heating and cooling system that operates on similar physics to a refrigerator (taking warm air and turning it into cool air, and the inverse).
2. The Heat-Pump has an outdoor unit, you've definitely seen them outside some homes. Usually it's a metal box about 3&amp;quot; cubed with a fan.
3. They don't tell you that's just the &lt;em&gt;outdoor&lt;/em&gt; part of the Heat-Pump, there is also a huge freaking indoor unit that converts chemical energy into warm/cool air that gets pumped around your house.
4. Heat-pumps are fully electric so no gas!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that's how a Heat-Pump works.
A few stars aligned for this to work out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our house already has vents that the oil furnace used to heat the house. This means we can easily heat/cool the entire house with one indoor unit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had some extra cash we didn't end up needing for our down-payment, so we were able to pay in cash saving us a lot in interest payments for the Heat-Pump (like 10%!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could have made it work without those happy coincidences; they make in-wall Heat-Pumps that heat/cool one or two rooms, and we could have financed if we were strapped for cash, or we could have just kept the old gas furnace.
But we &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; able to upgrade our central-air because 6 months later Portland had a 118℉ heat wave and another 100℉+ heat wave the day before our wedding!
Both of which we barely worried about because we were fortunate enough to have AC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="life-after-renting"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Life after renting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this post showed some of the awesome pros of home ownership, like being able to add a patio, with some healthy cons, like having to spend 12k on a new furnace.
We were able to get rid of the gas guzzling heating system in favor of a full-electric system.
We were able to build a patio, add a raised bed, fuck up the yard, without asking anybody for permission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a lot of work, and a lot of money sometimes, but it is empowering to be able to &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; your house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next post we'll throw all this soft &amp;quot;american dream&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;empowered to change&amp;quot; stuff out the window and figure out if this is a good investment!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="housing"></category><category term="housing"></category><category term="life"></category><category term="HGTV"></category></entry><entry><title>Buying a House Part 2: Show Me The Money!</title><link href="elijahcaine.me/buying-a-house-02-show-me-the-money" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-12-21T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-12-21T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Elijah Voigt</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-12-21:elijahcaine.me/buying-a-house-02-show-me-the-money</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Getting an offer accepted is half the battle!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is part 2 of a 4 part series on buying a home&lt;/em&gt;
Check out &lt;a class="reference external" href="buying-a-house-01-lets-go-shopping"&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; for to start from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post we will talk about everything that happens between getting an offer accepted on a house and your move-in day.
How exciting!
Let's get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="so-you-got-an-offer-accepted"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So you got an offer accepted&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You slogged through the home-buying process, your heart was broken in 12 pieces when you barely didn't get &amp;quot;the one&amp;quot; and then &amp;quot;the other one&amp;quot; and finally &amp;quot;the real one&amp;quot;, but you powered through and now you have an offer accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great, you're half way done!
Just kidding, this part is much easier, but it is time consuming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now in theory you can skip all these steps with a shit-ton of money and taking a shot of unnecessary risk.
I mean you can pay in cash for a house &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; waive home inspections to expedite the home-buying process.
I only have one anecdote of this happening, and the guy who told it to me was a prick, so I'm pretty sure it's fake news.
The only reason you would pay in cash is to avoid paying mortgage fees and to close the deal faster.
The only reason you would waive inspections is to make close on the house faster if you don't care or really trust the current owner.
Mortgage rates are bonkers low right now, and most people aren't in &lt;em&gt;that much&lt;/em&gt; of a rush to close on their house, so again: fake news.
For normal people with a normal amount of debt and a sane income we do things the way I'm about to describe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Steps down from soap-box&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that your offer is accepted you have a 30 day clock.
At the end of those 30 days you will hopefully have a house.
Very cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="inspections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Inspections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step is to schedule home inspections.
Your realtor should do this.
You will schedule a standard home inspection, but you can also request special inspections if you are concerned.
For example we tested for Radon and buried oil tanks, because both of those are shitty things in Portland.
These inspections are one of the few fees paid by the buyer because you as the buyer can be as picky as you want about the inspections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the inspections happen you'll do a walk-through.
Often this is the &lt;em&gt;second time you have seen the house in person&lt;/em&gt;, which I just find hilarious.
The inspector should walk you through the house and tell you literally everything wrong with the house that they can find.
They might also mention any concerns they have based on the listing's disclosures and the year the house was built/renovated.
The inspector shouldn't have any horse in this race, they're getting paid weather the deal falls through or not, so they should be pretty matter-of-fact.
This means they might tell you some scary shit like &amp;quot;This ceiling is probably asbestos, don't touch it until you get that tested&amp;quot;, this is just because you need to know everything that might be a deal breaker before the next step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the walk-through is complete your inspector will write up an inspection report and send it to you and your realtor for you to review and keep.
This is a very long, very boring, and very important document.
Keep a copy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="negotiations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Negotiations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you know everything about the house:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disclosures given in the house listing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inspection results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You've been inside like... twice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can enter the negotiation phase fully informed.
Negotiations are not done in a board room -- I wish -- they're done asynchronously by the seller and buyer's realtors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You sit down &lt;strong&gt;with your realtor&lt;/strong&gt; and go over the inspection results.
If your realtor is good they'll basically do the negotiation for you, reviewing what the plan is before locking it in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, our realtor said the following:
* The pipes are clogged with baby wipes or something, that can take 7k to fix so let's ask to knock off 7k.
* The garage door is busted, let's ask to take 5k off for that.
* Some other stuff got knocked off but I don't remember it a year later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We figure out how much to ask for by basically looking up how much it would reasonably cost to fix broken shit.
If your roof was caving in you would be able to ask to take a lot, if a stair was busted that would probably be less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can't get away with asking for price reductions for &lt;em&gt;aesthetic&lt;/em&gt; differences, like you wish the house had more outlets, but you could ask to get the price knocked if the electrical was unsafe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your realtor should then write this up and send it to the seller's realtor who will respond with a counter.
Sometimes they will choose to fix broken things themselves or they may drop the price for a given request.
In our case the owner dropped the price a bit, around 3k, and spent her own money to fix clogged pipes, which cost a few thousand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the negotiation the seller has an incentive to keep the final price fairly high while the buyer has an incentive to get the price as low as possible.
This means sellers might find more expensive quotes and the buyer might find cheaper quotes for repair costs.
But both parties have an incentive to complete the sale of the house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a seller refuses to negotiate on the price of the house, the buyer at this point has the option to pull out of the deal.
The buyer will most likely get their Earnest Money back because they found something out about the house after the offer was accepted which the buyer refused to fix or decrease the price for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="but-what-does-the-bank-think-it-s-worth"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But what does the bank think it's worth?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After negotiating on a price the bank gets involved again.
It takes the bank under a week to, given the home inspection plus their piles of data, determine what they think it's worth.
This has very little to do with what you thought it was worth and it is what the bank is willing to cover in the form of a home loan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the bank decides the house is worth &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; than the final offer you're golden.
You get a loan for the negotiated price and it'll be 100% covered by the bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example: If the final offer is 100k and the bank decides the house is worth 105k, you need to do the normal 20% down payment, and then you get an 80k loan for the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... But if the bank decides the house is worth &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; than the final offer you're some amount of fucked.
You need to pay the difference out of pocket, or pull out of the deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example: If the final offer is 100k but the bank decides the house is worth 60k, you need to cover 20k down payment, plus the 20k difference on the remaining cost.
100k - 20k = 80k ideal loan.
80k - 20k = 60k what the bank will actually loan you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note, I'm using 100k as a round number for math examples.
This is not some cruel joke, it's just easier numbers.
Most houses we looked at were between 350k and 600k.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="side-note-why-do-we-need-down-payments"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Side note, why do we need down payments?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait, why do we have down payments?
It's complicated, but I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; it's a collection of reasons:
* The more you pay up front, the less monthly payments you have. 20% up front is a good way to reduce your monthly payments from the get-go.
* Credit worthiness or some bullshit. Banks want to make sure you have skin in the game, so before you can get approved for a loan you need to prove you have 20%+ of the cost of the house for them to cover the other 80%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's my best bet.
Ask a realtor or your local economist or banker or something; they'll probably have a better answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the bank settles on a price you can close on the house.
You'll get a real loan for the final price (minus the difference you've paid in cash).
Finally, 30 days (ish) after getting your offer accepted you'll walk into a title company, go over a stack of papers with a professional, sign a bunch of those papers, and walk out the proud owner of a house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-now"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What now?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had to wait a few weeks after closing to actually move in.
The previous owner needed the funds from closing to close on her own house, but that ended up going faster than expected so we only had to stay at my parents house (#privilege #safetynet) for two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your realtor should give you some keys for the new house.
I suggest throwing those out once you're moved in and replace the locks -- even in a nice neighborhood, you have no idea who has the old keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rent a moving van and bribe your friends, or hire some movers if you're smart, and enjoy your beautiful house!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait, is this pipe supposed to be leaking?
In the next post we'll talk about home renovations!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="housing"></category><category term="housing"></category><category term="life"></category><category term="HGTV"></category></entry><entry><title>Buying a House Part 1: Let's Go Shopping!</title><link href="elijahcaine.me/buying-a-house-01-lets-go-shopping" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-08-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Elijah Voigt</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-08-26:elijahcaine.me/buying-a-house-01-lets-go-shopping</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;So you're interested in buying a house eh?&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So you're interested in buying a house eh?
Well boy howdy do I have a series of blog posts for you.
This four part series will equip you, a first-time home buyer, with a bunch of knowledge I wish I had before starting my journey to buying a home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the road-map:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/buying-a-house-01-lets-go-shopping"&gt;Part 1: 🛒 Let's Go Shopping!&lt;/a&gt; in which we start looking for houses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/buying-a-house-02-show-me-the-money"&gt;Part 2: 💸 Show Me the Money!&lt;/a&gt; in which we buy a freaking house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/buying-a-house-03-renovation-station"&gt;Part 3: 👷 Renovation Station.&lt;/a&gt; in which we live in the freaking house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 4: &lt;strong&gt;📈 Is This Investing?&lt;/strong&gt; where we figure out if we made a huge financial mistake (or achievement!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="hey-quick-disclaimer"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hey, quick disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some things I &lt;strong&gt;can&lt;/strong&gt; claim to be an expert on: Docker, Linux, why my dog is making that face, etc.
But with home-buying I am at best a novice, so please take everything you read here with a grain of salt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am just one lowly home owner in his mid-20s who bought a house during a pandemic.
I got here through a bunch of privilege, support, luck, and the modest amount amount of hard work &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt; to live a wonderful mortgage-filled life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not a financial advisor, realtor, none of that stuff.
I encourage you to do independent research, check my work, etc.
Don't make any decisions based purely on this series.
Please use it as one of many sources in your research before buying a house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, &lt;strong&gt;now&lt;/strong&gt; we can get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="so-um-why-do-you-want-to-buy-a-house"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So um, why do you want to buy a house?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before diving into the home buying process, let's ask an annoyingly simple (but annoyingly effective) question: &amp;quot;why?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a million reasons to want to buy a house.
A few that come to mind are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You want more space or a yard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You want an investment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You want to be in a residential neighborhood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You want to fulfill the American Dream™.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now none of these &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; you to buy a house.
You could rent a house to get more space, invest in high yield assets to make passive income, etc. but a house tends to check &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; these boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My fiance (now wife) and I we were living in a small apartment before buying a house.
This apartment was perfect pre-COVID.
It was a 10-20 minutes walking commute to work, centrally located, and big enough to sleep, cook meals, and rest while being young 20-somethings living our best lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When COVID hit we though we could muddle through in the apartment, but around the 2 month mark we thought:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Hmm, this isn't gonna be the &amp;quot;Come on Morty. Just two weeks, we'll be in and out. Just a little pandemic to spice things up.&amp;quot; thing that we thought this would be...&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We looked for house rentals, but while there were hundreds of houses for sale there were almost no houses rentals available in the Portland area.
I was always resistant to buying a house, but after realizing it was a reasonable financial decision we got started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where our home buying journey begins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="let-s-triage"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Let's triage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before buying a house, or even visiting a house, you should go to sites like Zillow and Redfin to get a lay of the land.
They both have basically the same home listings, so choose whichever site has a better interface for you.
This goes without saying though; you found this obscure blog post so you're probably deeply familiar with all the different home buying sites.
I promise this series will start saying less &amp;quot;yeah duh&amp;quot; stuff in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We knew roughly what neighborhoods we wanted to live in: East Portland with a bias toward the Tabor neighborhoods.
This made it quick to narrow our search and skip the existential question &amp;quot;where in the world do I want to live?&amp;quot; I'm sure some people confront.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="money-talk"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Money talk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have a feel for the housing market in your target locations, check in with your finances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="a-big-wad-of-cash"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A big wad of cash&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buying your soon-to-be house will require a down-payment.
This means you'll need a very big pile of money &lt;em&gt;very soon&lt;/em&gt;.
Figure out what your liquid assets (savings, non-retirement investment accounts, dubious favors you can call in) talley up to.
This is the max you could use for a down-payment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Down payments tend to be 20% of the purchase price of the house, and houses are hundreds of thousands of dollars, so... yeah that's a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have 20k in usable assets, you can afford a down payment on a 100k house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;84k usable assets? 420k house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13.8k usable assets? 69k house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sets an upper-limit on which houses you can afford.
Hopefully this upper-limit lines up with median home prices in your target neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="a-smaller-monthly-wad-of-cash"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A smaller monthly wad of cash&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also need to consider the monthly cost of your potential home.
Ideally you only spend up to 30% of your monthly income on living expenses.
This means your house (with utilities) costs no more than 30% of what you take home.
Some of you may be laughing at this because it is in fact an outdated metric that has not kept up with inflating home prices.
Don't worry, we'll cover how terrible home prices are in a later installment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 30% rule says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you take home 2k/month (roughly a 30k/year salary after taxes) your housing should cost no more than 600/month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5833/month (100k salary) take-home? 1750 housing expenses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11452/month (200k salary) take-home? 3435 housing expenses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what does that translate to for home prices?
You don't pay for the whole house up front (the bank does that).
Instead you pay for it in monthly installments with interest -- which is hard for me to intuit.
Skipping some prelude:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your house is 100k, you put up a 20k down payment, and you acquire a 30 year loan with 4% interest, your monthly payment will be ~587.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;200k house, 40k down, 4% interest 30yr loan? ~1070.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these numbers, as the price of the house goes up the monthly payments go up sub-linearly.
This means so a 400k house is a little less than 2000/month, ec.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no idea how to calculate these numbers by hand, I always use a calculator... &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.zillow.com/mortgage-calculator/"&gt;https://www.zillow.com/mortgage-calculator/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have established you can afford both the down-payment and monthly payments now we can start shopping!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If prices in your target neighborhood are out of reach, explore other candidates; neighborhoods near your targets, or even the 'burbs.
Also if you just like shopping for homes for the kick of it, because shopping is fun, power to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="get-yourself-a-realtor"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Get yourself a realtor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A realtor is like a lawyer.
You never &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; one, but they are incredible necessary for some of life's biggest shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were #blessed to have a family friend that was an active realtor; her name is Mary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relationship we had with our realtor was like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every week around Tuesday we would send her a list of houses we wanted to see. Between 5-10 houses every week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Occasionally she would also find a house she thought we would be interested in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first week she picked about half the houses to get a feel for what we were interested in, and we brought some we found on our own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She would drive us around to these houses, because we refuse to buy a car and she is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; nice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mary would schedule a time for us to visit the house, around 30 minutes per house, during this time we were the only ones in the homes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a card-carrying realtor Mary had special privileges not given to us normies, and information not found on public sites.
For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mary had a list of things disclosed about the house like &amp;quot;It's very full of asbestos&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;It's full of radon&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;The roof caved in last year, just fixed&amp;quot;. Info you would want to know before putting an offer on a house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She also had access to some cloak-and-dagger shit that let her into all of the houses on the market. Ever seen a lock-box on a for-sale house? She could open that lock-box and get the key out with an app on her phone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She also knew how to fill out the copious forms needed to put an offer on a house, but we'll get to that in the next post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="so-many-houses"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So. Many. Houses.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In total we were house shopping for about 5 weeks.
We averaged visiting 10 houses per week, doing 1 to 2 trips per week and visiting 6 houses per trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We saw a lot of houses.
Some great houses in safe boring neighborhoods far from where we wanted to live.
Some terrible houses that people kept calling &amp;quot;fixer-uppers&amp;quot; like they were in the pocket of big shitty house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of houses that were great except for like... one really important thing.
Some houses had a great location but were too small.
Or the house was the perfect size but too far from our target location.
Or the price and size were good but the neighbors were burning a literal pile of trash and they were like... very good at it, implying this wasn't a one-off thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point is, there were a lot of houses.
A lot that were good, many more that were non-starters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first week or two was basically a mulligan.
So many houses are so bad you start to think &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; houses are bad and you trick yourself into settling.
DO NOT SETTLE.
This is a huge freaking purchase, grind it out and you will find a house you like.
It might be at the upper end of your budget, or it might be a &lt;em&gt;little bit of a fixer upper&lt;/em&gt;, but you'll know the perfect house when you find it.
And you will &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; know when it's &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the right house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="getting-on-your-knees-and-asking-the-bank-for-a-pre-approval"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting on your knees and asking the bank for a pre-approval&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point in the story we haven't bought any houses yet, but before you are allowed to &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; about buying a house you need to get a bank to say &amp;quot;Yeah they're good for it&amp;quot;.
This requires asking a bank pretty please, giving them like 3 years of financial, employment, and credit records.
If you're buying this with a partner they need to do the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our case we tried to get a super cheap loan but we were told our offer might get rejected if we didn't have a &amp;quot;local loan&amp;quot; meaning a loan provided by a local Oregon company -- what year is it 1980?
In the end all of our loan options were super cheap, even the local ones, so we shrugged and told ourselves the cheapest loan probably had a bunch of closing fees that would basically cancel out the higher mortgage rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;fun fact&lt;/em&gt; about the loan process is that you get pre-approved for a loan up to some amount, which is used to put an offer on a house.
Once the offer is accepted you get the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; loan for whatever the final loan amount ends up being.
But we're getting ahead of ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-offer-process"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The offer process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point you'll make an offer on a house.
This might &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; like we're buying a house, but trust me there are a lot more offers on houses than there are sales on houses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you put in an offer on a house you basically roll for initiative and if you get a Nat-20 it gets accepted.
You should still treat every offer as if it were to be accepted, because you can roll a Nat-20 on a persuasion check with a rat just as often as slaying a dragon.
Offers are accepted and rejected basically at random, but each one is important and should be treated as &amp;quot;the one&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When putting an offer on a house you fill out a bunch of complicated legal-ese forms with your realtor.
Taking your pre-approval you decide on an offer up to your pre-approval limit.
In Portland right now we need to offer &lt;em&gt;way more&lt;/em&gt; than the asking price which is bullshit and I hate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also fill out a bunch of details like when you want the sale to be complete (30 days), weather you're planning on doing inspections (yes), and how much money you can put up &lt;em&gt;before your down payment&lt;/em&gt;.
That pre-down-payment is called Earnest Money and it's often between 2k and 10k, it counts toward your down payment, and it can be refunded if the deal falls through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="it-s-a-marathon-pace-yourself"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It's a marathon, pace yourself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucy went into this expecting that buying a house was like buying anything else.
You find what you like, offer a fair (or listed) price, and boom you get it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately housing is not like buying a phone, or basically anything else most people spend money on.
In Portland at least supply does not match demand, so prices are not only higher than they ought to be, but the prices are also &lt;em&gt;full of lies&lt;/em&gt;.
The asking price is often 10% below the final price -- if you're lucky!
Plus your offer on a house may be rejected for mysterious reasons.
More than once we were asked to re-submit an offer and to give our &amp;quot;highest and best&amp;quot; offer whatever the fuck that means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be prepared to visit at &lt;strong&gt;dozens&lt;/strong&gt; of houses.
Be prepared to make an offer on multiple houses.
You will have your heart broken when you find the perfect house, just to have it swiped out of your hands by a bank, somebody paying all in cash, somebody waiving inspections, or just some jerk that got an offer in half an hour before you did -- that bastard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take your time.
This is a big purchase.
It will pay off.
It will get better.
Your patience will be rewarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck.
See you in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="buying-a-house-02-show-me-the-money"&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt; where we get to buy a freaking house!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="housing"></category><category term="housing"></category><category term="life"></category><category term="HGTV"></category></entry></feed>