<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>elijahcaine.me - personal</title><link href="elijahcaine.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="elijahcaine.me/feeds/personal.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>elijahcaine.me/</id><updated>2017-12-12T00:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>I. Fucking. Graduated.</title><link href="elijahcaine.me/i-fucking-graduated" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-12T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-12-12T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Elijah Voigt</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-12-12:elijahcaine.me/i-fucking-graduated</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;I fucking graduated. Fuck yes.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I checked my grades for the last time.
I can safely say that I have &lt;strong&gt;finally&lt;/strong&gt; gotten a gorramn undergraduate degree in Computer Science, with a minor in Mathematics, from Oregon State University. &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id5" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id7" id="id2"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hear that this happens on the reg &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id6" id="id3"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; but I'm sure that every single person who &lt;em&gt;actually graduates&lt;/em&gt; feels amazing when they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not amazing because graduation is a Herculean feat.
I know I'm not a 60 year old grandmother who dreamt of getting a college degree for 45 years and finally scraped together the cash and time in retirement.
I'm also not a refugee that escaped a war-torn country for an education and a better life.
I'm just another white dude that checked all the boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn't hard for me.
I just had to put my head down and do the work.
But it did take a long ass time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly my story is exactly like &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; college graduation stories.
I went to kindergarten, then elementary school, then middle school, then high school, then college, and now life.
I plugged away at school, did what I needed to pass my classes, stressed and lamented, studied hard and eventually the system said &amp;quot;Cool. You're done.&amp;quot;
Along the way I learned how to &amp;quot;play the game&amp;quot; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id8" id="id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;, albeit a bit late compared to a lot of my peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm thankful to be in a field which doesn't require a masters or PHD to get a jorb.
Heck my field doesn't really require the degree I got; a surprising number of my friends got well paying jobs sans-degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm also thankful to graduate without debt.
This came from some kickass parents + grandparents, some work during school, and some bad stuff that happened which ended up paying for abou half of my tuition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm thankful to graduate with wonderful friends, a job, and some passions which make my work-related decisions simple and profitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last, I'm thankful to be &lt;em&gt;done&lt;/em&gt;.
Now I can finally focus on &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt;, my real passion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm gonna have a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://10barrel.com/beer/crush-cucumber-sour/"&gt;Cucumber Sour&lt;/a&gt; and celebrate.
Thanks for reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id5" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;I don't claim to have the best sources, but at least it's not Yahoo Answers:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.reference.com/education/many-people-graduate-college-year-8b0ccf821050d39e"&gt;https://www.reference.com/education/many-people-graduate-college-year-8b0ccf821050d39e&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id6" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id3"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;I'm 99% sure I graduated. Something horribly kafkaesque might still happen, but fuckit.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id7" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id2"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Go beavs.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id8" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;This is shorthand for tips and tricks to get through school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;School isn't really focused on making sure you &lt;em&gt;learned&lt;/em&gt;, it's mostly designed to make sure you can pass tests.
Once you figure this out you can focus on learning for the test instead of trying to grok the material.
I believe the kids call it a &amp;quot;life hack&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not that you shouldn't try to grok the material, that just happens to take &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; longer than test-based learning.
So if you want a personal life, learn for the test; if you want a PHD, learn for the material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="last"&gt;I didn't figure this system out until about Junior year of High School, too late to apply this zen skill to the ACT and SAT, but it was useful in college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="Persona"></category><category term="Graduation"></category></entry></feed>